<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on notes and stuff</title>
    <link>https://jlbar.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on notes and stuff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 08:08:54 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jlbar.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Periodicity in Financial Time Series</title>
      <link>https://jlbar.github.io/post/08-29-2016_fourier-transform/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 08:08:54 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbar.github.io/post/08-29-2016_fourier-transform/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I will make a first pass through several sources, then condense my notes into
something more unified and coherent. Each source will have its own section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourier-transform-and-its-applications&#34;&gt;The Fourier Transform and its Applications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://see.stanford.edu/materials/lsoftaee261/book-fall-07.pdf&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;periodic-phenomena&#34;&gt;Periodic Phenomena&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important principle of the subject at hand is the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And another edit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every signal has a spectrum and is determined by its spectrum. You can analyze
the signal either in the time (or spatial) domain or in the frequency domain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;time-and-space&#34;&gt;Time and Space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and stuff&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think about periodic phenomena in two distinct contexts: &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an event is periodic in time, the phenomenon comes to you. Examples include
sound and waves on a shoreline. When an event is periodic in space, you come to
the phenomenon. An example is observing a picture and noting repeating patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physically, the fourier transform will represent the frequency components of a
function or signal. A fundamental result of fourier series states that any
periodic phenomena may be expressed as a combination of sines and cosines of
varying frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;analysis-of-financial-time-series-using-fourier-and-wavelet-methods&#34;&gt;Analysis of Financial Time Series using Fourier and Wavelet Methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.664.9412&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a set of methods in the field of &lt;em&gt;frequency domain
analysis&lt;/em&gt;. Spectral analysis and filtering methods are two important techniques.
Spectral analysis can be used to identify the different frequency components of
a time series. Filters allow us to capture trends, cycles, and seasonality.
Filters may also be used to eliminate specific frequency components from the
original time series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part of the paper discusses wavelets. Frequency domain analysis
techniques such as fourier analysis eliminate the time domain altogether from
the representation. Only the frequency domain is present in the representation.
Wavelets are unique and attractive in that they provide a complete
representation from both the time and the frequency domains simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, wavelets do not suffer from many of the traditional limitations of
frequency domain methods. A &lt;em&gt;stationary&lt;/em&gt; time series is one whose statistical
properties (mean, variance, autocorrelation, etc.) are all constant over time.
Spectral methods and fourier transforms require stationary data. This is very
often not the case in the financial domain. Volatility may manifest in many
forms due to many external factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;frequency-domain-analysis&#34;&gt;Frequency Domain Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will divide the discussion of frequency analysis into two sections: one on
&lt;em&gt;spectral analysis&lt;/em&gt; and one on &lt;em&gt;filtering techniques&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;spectral-analysis&#34;&gt;Spectral Analysis&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field of time series analysis involves the study of a variable in the time
domain. Spectral analysis, on the other hand, studies the properties of a
variable over the frequency domain. Specifically, the goal is to explain the
variance in a variable by describing how the variance may be split into a
variety of frequency components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://robjhyndman.com/hyndsight/longseasonality/&#34;&gt;http://robjhyndman.com/hyndsight/longseasonality/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.nsc.ru/AP/ScientificDiscovery/PDF/data_mining_for_financial_applications.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.math.nsc.ru/AP/ScientificDiscovery/PDF/data_mining_for_financial_applications.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.le.ac.uk/users/dsgp1/COURSES/LEIMETZ/FOURIER.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.le.ac.uk/users/dsgp1/COURSES/LEIMETZ/FOURIER.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.nsc.ru/AP/ScientificDiscovery/PDF/data_mining_for_financial_applications.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.math.nsc.ru/AP/ScientificDiscovery/PDF/data_mining_for_financial_applications.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.nsc.ru/AP/ScientificDiscovery/PDF/data_mining_for_financial_applications.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.math.nsc.ru/AP/ScientificDiscovery/PDF/data_mining_for_financial_applications.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>first</title>
      <link>https://jlbar.github.io/post/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 14:31:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbar.github.io/post/first/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a trial post for the first iteration of this project. I am using Hugo to
generate a static website and Github Pages for deployment. This text should be
sufficient to determine if everything is working as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>